<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-21T16:57:48-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Ikigai</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/11/25/ikigai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ikigai" /><published>2018-11-25T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-11-25T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/11/25/ikigai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/11/25/ikigai.html">&lt;p&gt;Some of my readers may know that I recently decided what I’ll be doing past high school: studying computer science. This is very exciting as I now feel much more focused and fulfilled. I do find now that it is strange sitting in English classes and the like and trying to stay as motivated as I was. I now know that this subject won’t be consequential to my life. However, I still enjoy all of my classes and have loved my school year so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I want to touch on in this piece is how I came to that decision. It’s a very muggy thing, trying to decide what you’re going to do after high school, and there’s mounds of questionable advice out there. “Follow your passion!” is one quip I hear a lot. This is terrible advice. Your passion alone should not inform what you do, because it might not make sense with a few others things: what you’re good at, what the world actually needs, and what you can make money for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a little research, and stumbled across the Japanese concept of ikigai. Of course, I won’t explain it perfectly, so I encourage you to check this out on your own, but I’ll try my best. Ikigai is a Japanese term for “a reason for being,” similar to ‘raison d’etre’ and other expressions. In the culture of Okinawa, ikigai is thought of as “a reason to get up in the morning.” Seems pretty cool right? So what does it actually look like? Well, I’ll start with this venn diagram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/ikigai.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ikigai&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A four way venn diagram, so maybe not totally clear. Let’s try to understanding what’s going on. There are four categories, as mentioned. What you love, what you can be paid for, what the world needs, and what you’re good at. Each of these intersect to fill different roles in our life: profession, vocation (a side hustle or a “calling”), mission, and passion. Now it’s clear how passion alone is dangerous: it doesn’t factor in money or the world at large. At the center of all of these concepts is harmony: ikigai. There are also cautions surrounding the venn diagram. Let’s dissect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without having what the world needs, we feel “satisfaction, but a feeling of uselessness.” In our lives, we need to contribute to something greater, and to feel a higher purpose (regardless of our spirituality). Across from that is where we lack any money behind our work; we have “delight and fullness, but no wealth.” Don’t get too caught up in money though, there’s a minimum you have to maintain to lead a satisfying life, and beyond that money begins to dictate your personality. What that baseline is varies from person-to-person, but try to determine what life you want to lead, and this can inform your salary goals. On the bottom right it reads, “excitement and complacency, but sense of uncertainty.” In this example, we haven’t taken advantage of our skills. This would create a similar apathy and sadness, as we feel we could achieve something greater. Lastly, to the left from there, it reads: “comfortable, but a feeling of emptiness.” We need to have work that we love, otherwise, we dive deep into our work. Your life’s achievements need to have a personal element to them to bring you joy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it: ikigai. A tangible way to think about what you want to do with your life. There are no wrong answers with ikigai, and if you ever feel you are missing something, you’re never at a dead end. There are always chances to pick up a new hobby, work with a new organization, or challenge yourself somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and how did I use ikigai to decide my major? I focussed on the intersection between what I was good at, and what I could be paid for. The world needs a lot of things, and there are lots of bright people working towards those things in their careers, so I didn’t want that to necessarily inform my major. I’ll put a pause on world domination for now. Moreover, I’m the type that loves virtually all of my work, so I didn’t find that helpful in deciding. So, I had narrowed it down to what made money. Countless jobs have a salary I would be more than happy with. Some that stuck out included work in academia, STEM-centered jobs, potentially even law. Then I thought about what I was good at. I’m pretty flexible, but at more core I have a few main talents: math, problem-solving, and communicating. Well, a job that fuses that quite well is in computer science, where problems must be solved and presented to consumers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about ikigai, you’re always welcome to reach out at me@michaeldemar.co. I also encourage you to check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forastateofhappiness.com/ikigai-the-happiness-of-always-being-busy-in-japan/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael</name></author><summary type="html">In a world filled with choices, what path should you take? Follow your heart? Live to make money and hope fulfillment follows? I use a Japanese model called &quot;Ikigai&quot; to try to answer this monstrous question.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Declassified School Survival Guide</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/05/15/school-survival-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Declassified School Survival Guide" /><published>2018-05-15T12:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T12:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/05/15/school-survival-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/self-help/2018/05/15/school-survival-guide.html">&lt;p&gt;High school is complicated in more ways than one. From Degrassi-esque social drama to life-altering career decisions, it can be seriously difficult to maintain your grades. However, there are some simple tricks to ease the learning process and make your education systematic - that is, without all the overhead of figuring how to do this whole school thing. By following these three tips, you’ll surely see a boost in your productivity and an ease in your hectic high school life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the schedule. Scheduling is no easy task! But nothing will hinder your high school experience more than not even being able to see what’s in front of you. Scheduling has a myriad of benefits, from being able to see hectic exams days in advance, giving yourself free-time, and preventing yourself from double booking. One of the most common high school troubles is when teachers schedule numerous projects and exams for the same day. I like to call this “the slog.” The easiest way to get out of the slog is to jump out in front of it. You’ll be surprised how receptive teachers are if you let them know early on that you won’t be able to turn something in; however, teachers will not hesitate to dock you marks if you let them know the day of. All of this comes from scheduling. The easiest way to get started is to use an app like Google Calendar. This allows you to sync from your phone to your computer, and you can catch overlaps in your schedule as soon as they appear. Once you’re comfortable with using Google Calendar, try to set a daily time to determine your schedule for the next day or week. This way, your studying time and project work periods can also be booked before they get away from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the strategy. By high school, you likely have a good sense of what style of learner you are. But don’t fret about the often exclaimed learner categories — be it “aural,” “visual,” or “kinesthetic” — these terms are often too narrow for most students. Instead, work class-by-class. In math, does it help more to do loads of practice or to do just the difficult questions? In English, do you need to spend more time planning, or are you better off working through your ideas as you write? Explicitly outlining these strategies, analogous to you being your own coach, can help you consciously approach your learning. Be flexible with this though! If a strategy is failing, just like a great coach, switch it up. As long as you’re sure of yourself, your learning strategy is more likely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last of all, the life. Though it may be tempting at times, when you’re bracing for a scholarship and pushing for a spot at your favoured university, never let school trump your personal endeavours. Always maintain the activities you enjoy to ensure both your mental and physical health through the often tumultuous times. Eat three times a day, and try beginning your mornings with protein-heavy breakfasts. Sugar-rich cereals do little to boost your energy throughout the day, but a morning protein boost can give you that crucial edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to maintain these three things - the schedule, the strategy, and the life - is the crux of living your best life in high school. First and foremost, put your best foot forward, with these ambitions and motives in the back of your mind, and you’ll be sure to thrive throughout high school.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael</name></author><summary type="html">Here are my thoughts on surviving high school.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Love to Hate</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/commentary/2018/05/12/love-to-hate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love to Hate" /><published>2018-05-12T12:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-05-12T12:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/commentary/2018/05/12/love-to-hate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/commentary/2018/05/12/love-to-hate.html">&lt;p&gt;Youth are a being of change. Changemakers. Worldshakers. We possess an unshakeable ingenuity and creativity that experience and time works to harden into immutability. However, being born into our particular circumstances, it is easy to become resentful of what lies ahead. Humans, innately, desire choice and fear constraint. It’s an experience I’ll coin ‘visceral claustrophobia,’ where we feel suffocated by decades of guilt. When told us young Canadians are responsible for the Residential School System, the natural reaction is to get angry. Throw our fists in the air. It’s a backwards emotion, actively working to counteract progress and productive thought. It’s far from unique to Canadians either. The high school students from Stoneman Douglas in Parkland, Florida were crushed under the weight of institutional levy in the form of the NRA. When Senator Marco Rubio (R-FL) began to work on a bill with Democratic Senator Bill Nelson (D-FL), he was still chastised. The criticism was partly justified, but is antithetical to progress. We need to grow out of our overly antagonistic shell, and learn to create. Learn to love. Find guidance within wise generations and see that experience and ingenuity can intertwine, not clash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response to the tragedy in Parkland, Florida was enormous and awe-inspiring. It’s analogous to the counterculture of the 1960s that was similarly championed by disaffected young people and who were enabled by affluence (in the 60’s, it was post-war riches). Even my speech and debate class sat down and analyzed David Hogg’s mannerisms; his talent was truly unmistakable. However, and through no fault of the students of Parkland, it was marked by mistakes. These weren’t dramatic mistakes in any way—the underlying motives of the movement were well intentioned and, overall, well-executed—but were assuredly a sign of adults willingness to use youth voice as a political tool, rather than a point of influence. They failed to mentor the students where it was needed most. To prevent vile, ill-advised statements such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;KASKY: I’m sorry, I know I’m not supposed to do this, but I’m not going to listen to that. Senator Rubio, it’s hard to look at you and not look down a barrel of an AR-15 and not look at Nicholas Cruz, but the point is you’re here and there some people who are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;—Cameron Kasky, student activist and cofounder of Never Again MSD (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2018/02/22/politics/cnn-town-hall-full-video-transcript/index.html&quot;&gt;CNN&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students of Parkland reminded me of the power of youth to make change. But they also reminded me of our limitations, if guided improperly. Even when progress seemed to come about for gun rights in America, the students failed to be receptive. Little evidence of effort to find common ground was present in the core principles of the #MarchForOurLives rally. I do agree that youth have a role to be outspoken, and bring radical, fresh ideas to a society that is quite calcified in its thinking. But some underlying sense of cooperation wouldn’t hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our generation—similar to most generations of young people—we would prefer to be divorced from reality and solve strawman issues. It’s tough to get into the nitty gritty. It would be easier to boil down international conflicts, gun legislation, workers rights, racism, and more into a black-and-white ‘good guy’ versus ‘bad guy’ issues. This habit is extremely underproductive. Recently, I watched a TED Talk from Jonathan Haidt entitled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/jonathan_haidt_on_the_moral_mind&quot;&gt;“The Moral Roots of Liberals and Conservatives,”&lt;/a&gt; and it’s definitely worth a watch. In fairness, Haidt has recently become a protractor of the “intellectual dark web” and leans conservative on many issues, yet his points in the lecture about the simple moral principles beneath any liberal or conservative unveil the easiest pathway to common ground, and that is to see the innate purpose in all political decisions. It is useless to vilify political actors or ‘big bad’ CEOs. They’re not a huffin’ and a puffin’ and a blowin’ society down. It’s comparable to pinning the blame of the Canadian Residential School System solely on Ottawa. Not only is it factually untrue, but it also makes it impossible to solve the issues. For example, Amazon’s managerial issues are somewhat to pin on Bezos; however, the issue in reality is far more complex, as it likely speaks to regional managers targeting their employees to impress those above them, and it only climbs the hierarchy from there. Moreover, it’s common for youth to oversimplify issues. The way unions are presented in the Albertan curriculum is effectively ‘they serve to protect workers and are wholly good for the workplace.’ I take no issue with the level of the material. The trouble is what youth then do with that prescribed knowledge, lurching into the real world with a toolbox half empty. Youth are great at pointing out issues that need to be addressed, but we are not so great at solving them. And this is exactly the shift in tone that needs to occur in young people; a being of recommendation, a voice of cause, but not a claimant of justified truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we desire to enter the political arena and enact change, we must be prepared to do so in a purposeful way. We would be more benefited by moving our legs than throwing our fists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael</name></author><summary type="html">Here are my thoughts on how to really make a difference.</summary></entry></feed>